What's the capabilities of Spring AI?
What does it provide? So, Spring AI is
your one-stop shop for AI engineering.
We in the Java and Spring communities in
particular are in a uniquely amazing
position right now because 90% of AI
engineering is writing text and sending
it to a rest endpoint. The magic of AI
is happening in OpenAI servers. For us,
this is just a REST call. There's no
schema. It's just human language text.
So, all of the interesting stuff you see
people doing today, your business logic,
the things that drive your business and
the data that feeds your business,
that's all governed and controlled by
and orchestrated by Springbased
microservices. Sure, some people are
going to use Eizen to train new models,
but that's not most of us. In the same
way that most of us aren't building our
own SQL database, most of us don't need
to do that either. How does AI fit into
all of this? So, you know, Spring is a
set of frameworks, Spring Boot on top of
that and a bunch of verticals on top of
that serving different use cases
including microservices, batch
processing, integration, data, security,
whatever, right? And we have one called
Spring AI, which goes GA by the way. I
just assumed it was GA just by the
amount I hear about it. It's mature.
People are using it. It's growing all
the time. It's very, very popular. But
obviously we've just wanted to get to a
point where we had the things that
mattered. And I think we're there.
[Music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI Native Dev and Jo. We're at Devox
UK today and joining me is the wonderful
Josh Long. Hi buddy. Josh, how are you
doing? Oh, so good. I'm I'm at DevOps
UK. DevOp as we dev. Um Josh, we go back
like how long? Many years. 15 years. Too
long. 2010 maybe. Yeah. Yeah, I think
so. And and and I I've been a fan since
2011.
Was 2010 a bad year. No, I'm just
kidding. No, that you I mean you you
created a you you brought so much joy to
my heart, but then you brought joy to
the world. I remember the the virtual
jug. Yes. That was I just think about
that all the time. That was such a
genius idea, a decade ahead of its time.
It took a pandemic for the rest of the
world to realize, oh yeah, genius. Yeah.
You know, and that's still going now.
There's almost 20,000 people in the
virtual jug these days. Wow. Apparently.
Apparently. It's crazy. So, um, people
know Josh Long as the Spring advocate,
the advocate in Java space. But, um, how
long have you been with, uh, with with,
uh, Spring, Pivotal, VMware, Broadcom? I
don't since 2010. 2010. uh and uh you
know still going strong but uh yeah it's
been about as long as I've known you
actually it's yeah it's been coincident
wonderful. Yeah. Awesome. And today
we're going to be talking about um
Spring AI we'll be talking uh a little
bit about uh perhaps why people will use
AI when they're typically a Java
developer, Spring developer. So we'll
talk a little bit uh about the reasoning
behind why people use it and then we'll
go into some demo as well to talk about
so actually show Spring AI in action.
But I guess first of all what's the
capabilities of Spring AI? What does it
what does it provide? So Spring AI is is
your one-stop shop for AI engineering
and uh I think we in the Java and Spring
communities in particular are in a
uniquely amazing position right now.
just an amazing position because where
uh most people are going to use AI is an
integration with their existing business
logic and applications and and services
that's all written in spring that's all
written on the JVM and cotlin and Java
and whatever right that that you're
already there they just want to hang AI
off integrations off of that code and
make it work your business logic the
things that drive your business and the
data that that that feeds your business
that's all governed and controlled by
and orchestrated by spring-based
microservices and so this is a really
natural place uh to start your AI
journey. I think is to enable access to
that data and to that business logic
from your AI models and via your AI AI
models. So uh sure some people are going
to use Python to train new models, but
that's not most of us. Most of us in the
same way that most of us aren't building
our own SQL database, you know, and C or
whatever. Uh most of us don't need to do
that either. Yeah. So I I think we're in
a uniquely great position. And when it
comes to production, production worthy,
scalable, fast, secure, uh, observable
production, that's, you know, the JVM
is, there's nothing like it. Nothing
like that, you know. Yeah. Yeah. Okay.
So, AI, how does AI fit into all of
this? Uh, well, we have this point of
view, right? We've got, so you know,
spring uh is a set of frameworks, spring
framework, and then spring boot on top
of that and a bunch of verticals on top
of that serving different use cases
including microservices, batch
processing, integration, data, uh,
security, whatever, right? And uh we
have one called Spring AI which goes GA
by the way 1.0 GA 20th of March, no May.
So we we had ambitions I think I think
uh I don't know if I'm speaking out of
school here or not. I think at one point
we hoped it would go GA. Uh but um and
you're not going to believe this. The AI
space has changed. Really? Yeah. I don't
believe it. No, I you you if there's one
if there's one constant, right, it's
it's the AI space. AI's change is too
much. um it's too quick, too fast, too
much too or whatever. We have a whole
team of people working on this. And even
they uh and we got, you know, it's one
of our most busy uh open source
projects, right? It's the star history
is like a hockey hockey puck, you know,
just hockey stick rather just just
through the roof meteoric rise in in
popularity and GitHub issues and and
contributions and everything. It's just
it's Yeah. So every time we think we're
about to settle down and reach a GA
mouse or GA release, whole new paradigm
gets dropped in our laps. I just I just
assumed it was GA just by the amount I
hear about it. It's mature. People are
using it. It's growing all the time.
It's it's very very popular. But
obviously we've just wanted to get to a
point where we had the things that
mattered and um I think we're there. So
as soon as there's a week of no change
or May 20th, whichever should happen,
whichever should happen first. Yeah.
Well, I think it's going to be May 20th
either way. At that point, we're we're
on the 7th of May. So, yeah, got a
couple weeks. Yeah, we don't even have
two weeks of that, you know. In fact,
depending on when this gets released.
Yeah, we could be around May 20th. It
may be May 27th, actually. Actually,
that might that may be 7 days too late.
Yeah. Really? So, let's just say let's
just say Spring AI is out today. Yeah,
it's out. Yeah. Okay. Go get the bits.
Fresh off the We might even have the
first patch release. Who knows? Yeah. by
the time you watch this. But all that to
say, things are moving quickly and
that's okay. That's okay. But remember,
we want to pair uh the innovation in the
AI space with the idiomatic uh sort of
approach to building apps that Spring
has always so embodied. And um we want
that to to build upon some of the
pillars that Spring has always talked
about, right? Portable service
abstractions to isolate you from the uh
differences between different models and
image models, chat models, transcription
models, etc. um uh dependency injection,
aspect oriented programming and the
spring boot style auto configuration,
you know. So you take those four pillars
and um did I say three earlier? I was
talking about four. Yeah. And uh you get
an approach that it gives you purchase
in this new strange land, right? It
gives you uh uh the ability to get hit
the ground running. You already know all
that stuff. You already know the
component model. It's just a matter of
applying that those those facets of your
understanding of Spring to this new
domain. And you're going to demo Spring
AI? I sure am. We'll talk a little bit
about as we go through. We're going to
build a very simple application here
because we're kind of pressed on time.
Uh but I wanted to demonstrate a simple
application that helps we're going to
build an assistant to help people adopt
dogs, right? And I talk about dogs all
the time because I think it's really
cute. And I've got I've got a dog and I
I talk about uh this in particular. I
talk about my dog who's Look, he's not
the best dog, but he's mine. And we'll
you know, we'll he's a good dog. He's
still a good dog. He's he's
Look at that dog. That's a that's a cute
dog right there. So, uh, all that to
say, um, not good, but he's ours. And
his name is Peanut. Okay. And Peanut is
the worst dog. Except then I met this
other dog in the we learned about this
other dog in the pandemic whose name is
Prancer. Prancer turns out even more of
a spicy uh dog, right? And this owner,
this lady was trying to find a new home
for this dog. And she put out this
hysterical ad saying, "Okay, I've tried.
I've tried for the last several months
to post this dog for adoption and make
him sound palatable. The problem is he's
just not. There's not a very big market
for neurotic, man-hating, animal-hating,
children hating dogs that look like
gremlins." And she continues, "If you
want a Chihuahua, you probably know what
I'm talking about. He's literally the
Chihuahua meme that describes him as
being 50% hate and 50% tremble." She
continues, "I kind of liked him better
that way. He was quiet and just laid on
the couch. Didn't bother anyone. I was
excited to see him come out of the shell
and become a real dog. I'm convinced at
this point that he's not a real dog, but
more like a vessel for a traumatized
Victorian child that now haunts our
home. And she continues and this goes on
for a long time and she signs off. Oh,
he's only 2 years old and will probably
live to be 21 through pure spite. So,
take that into account if you're
interested. That said, super cute,
right? Like that's a cute dog. I keep
that is a cute dog. I'd pet that dog.
Look at him. I've got two Labradors. I
got two Labradors. I don't know. The big
dogs are great.
But my dog just like this dog small.
They have the Napoleon complex, you
know, like the something about it. Yeah.
Angry. Angry by default by default. And
I don't know why because I just want to
I just want to pet this cute little guy.
Um so so I think about this dog a lot
too. Rentree all the time, right? I mean
just just how did such a dog exist? And
by the way, this ad went viral, right?
This ad went viral. So for example,
here's a People magazine talking about
Prancer the demonic Chihuahua. Here's um
USA Today talking about Prancer, the
demonic Chihuahua. Here's BuzzFeed
um talking about the nightmare
Chihuahua, the viral nightmare
Chihuahua. And of course, here's the New
York Times talking about Prancer, the
demonic Chihuahua, right? So, very very
famous dog. And I thought, well, that's
that's nice. That's good that people
learn about this dog, but that's not how
most people roll, right? Most people
don't find dogs by finding them on the
uh on the internet, right? like you go
to a shelter and you have a conversation
with somebody and you you interview to
to discover the dog of your dreams or in
this case uh nightmares. So what I
wanted to do is to build such an
assistant to help people go through that
process, right? To to find the right
dog. So we're going to go to
start.springo. Uh I've already got this
dog database here and you can see
there's our doggo prancer. His ID is 45
and his name is Prancer, right? He's in
a postgris database. So we're going to
build an application here. We're going
to call it assistant. Is Postgres
database strong enough to contain
Branson? Yeah, it's it is a very very
tough ask. Yeah, Gravm, we use the web
stuff. We use um Open AI. Now, I'm going
to use Open AI. It's just a very good
model and a lot of people probably have
access to it, but it's not the only
model. Not even close. you're in uh data
data privacycentric sensitive Europe,
you might prefer something a like a
llama which is a fine choice or uh you
know alternatively we got things like
bedrock and uh Gemini and um everything
everything I mean just there's dozens
and dozens of different models that we
officially support and the ones that we
don't officially support most of them
speak the uh open AI API and so you can
talk to them via our open AI integration
right so I'm going to bring in Open AI
I've got the web support, don't I? Oh, I
took that away. I'll bring in the spring
boot actuator support. Um, and I'm going
to bring in I need a a vector store.
Now, you can use, look, just type vector
store. And you can see you got Milvas,
you got Neo forj, Pine Cone, Mariab,
Wevate, Oracle, Reddus, uh, Cugrant,
Azour, Apache, Cassandra, Chroma,
Elastic Search, MongoDB, PG Vector,
Typesense, Azur, Cosmos DB, etc. I'm
going to use PG vector store because
I've got a SQL database in Postgres.
This is a a plugin, right? Vector
plugin. So, we're going to go ahead and
open that up. What you did there was you
added a bunch of down a bunch of
dependencies into your Spring project,
which then allows you to effectively
build that into I presume a Maven Pom
file. Yep. When you build that, it will
pull all the Java dependencies straight
into your uh into your Spring project.
You know it. And actually, you know what
I did? You know what I did wrong there?
I uh I forgot to select
uh PG. No, I forgot to select dev tools.
Okay. So, I'm gonna actually go down to
M7 here because I don't know what the
they changed something in M8 and I don't
remember the idiomatic way to do it
already, but I'll use that. It's
downloading the internet, which is not a
good thing. It's We're actually on
conference Wi-Fi. No, we're not. Stop
that. Stop it. No, the the go I'm used
I'm I'm live streaming here. Okay. So,
Intelligj is amazing, but if you start
the project in Intelligj before uh
adding the um dev tools, yeah, it'll
it'll not use it won't enable the dev
tools integration. Gotcha. So, I I
retroactively added the dev tools. Uh
there, didn't I?
I did not. Oh, that is so awkward. Okay,
we'll go back over here.
Copy and
paste. Dev to Tools is there now. Right.
There you go. So now we'll go back
again. Do this whole thing again.
Normally you don't have to do any of
this stuff, but I've scooted up twice
now. Mhm.
Okay.
Pom.xml and uh
M7. There we are. Fantastic. Reload. So
here's our
application. And we know we're going to
build a controller that'll act as a the
thing that we can ask questions to,
right? So system controller and uh just
have an endpoint here with a user
context and then the inquiry endpoint,
right? Uh inquire. So I'll say string
inquire and uh we're going to use to do
our work. We're going to talk to a chat
model. And that chat model, by the way,
is going to be connected. We're going to
connect to it via OpenAI. Uh and we have
a key there. Now, friends, I've already
I've already exported an environment
variable here like so. Right? So that's
already done in the my shell and spring
boot will normalize that into the
property that you just saw there a
second ago. These two are the same, but
you need to specify that yourself when
you connect. Okay, we're also going to
connect to a data source, not that one.
Spring data source uh URI JDBC
colostgrris QL, right? Local
host my database and then we'll create
the username my user and then the
password is secret. Okay, go back to
here and we're going to use the chat
client that was just uh we can it's got
a there's a chat model and then you can
use a chat client. You can create as
many of these chat clients as you want
that will talk to the chat model behind
the scenes. I'm going to inject the chat
client builder and build a new one. And
here I'm going to put my defaults and
then I'll use that model here to answer
questions from the user to this
endpoint. Right? So call.content
etc. And then the prompt is a user
prompt coming from uh the user and
that'll be a request parameter. Right.
Request param string uh
question. So confusing. Ignore this user
path variable for now. Okay. Mhm. Let's
just try this. So we're going to start
that up. Okay. So a user can hit that
endpoint that inquire endpoint asking
any questions as that as that as that
variable that param variable um that
request param that then goes to the chat
client which talks to the model stuff
talks to the model which is open AI in
this case. does some stuff, provides an
answer, passes it back to you here,
right? Says, "Nice to see you. Nice to
meet you, Josh. How can I assist you
today?" Great. So, it's We made it
wiggle, right? There's There's a dial
tone there. By the dog. By the dog.
Yeah. Right. Well, what's my name? I
don't have access to Okay. So, it does
It's already forgotten me. Y right.
Yeah. Quite like the first time we met
you. I said hi and you're like, "Ah."
And then moved on and we didn't talk for
a year. I can't believe you're lying,
John.
So, so uh anyway, it doesn't know. Yeah.
So we need to help it because remember
you use chat GBT use cloud desktop
whatever they have memory they have
conversational memory but that's not the
case for the models right APIs. So we
need to continue that context. We send
that context back to it every time.
Yeah. And the way you do that is by
creating a um uh uh configuring an
advisor. Okay. So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to have a per user uh map
you know and I'm going to pass this chat
memory
advisor. Okay. Mhm. So, up. There we go.
There we go. And I'll go down here and
then the
advisor the the map will say compute if
absent
user, right? And I'm just going to
create a new one if it doesn't exist and
I'll store it in memory. Now, there's
other implementations of this chat
memory interface y that you can use uh
that will write to different uh
abstractions, right? you can do like Neo
forj and JDBC and I think there's one
Reddus coming along I don't know but
it's all sorts of JDBC of course you
know all that stuff so okay this is an
advisor this is like a filter right uh
it's a pre-processor on the requests
intended for the model and basically as
we have a conversation with the model
this will get
um stored per user in that map and then
it's a transcript in effect of
everything we said and that'll be
retransmitted to the on every subsequent
request so that the model remembers oh
we talked about AB and C when the person
asks about AB and C uh remember it right
so here we go so now we go back and we
say uh my name is Josh
great what's my name your name is Josh
fine how do you do right so it's now got
memory uh but let's ask but this is
actually kind of a problem right like
which is a like um what's 2 plus two
right yeah okay great but it's not
supposed to be helping people with their
homework. It's supposed to be a model to
help people adopt a dog. Clearly, we've
got we've kind of wandered off in the
deep end here. And this is interesting
because you see a ton of companies. What
was the what was the the there was a
couple of big ones? I think one was was
it Eisler or someone where Yeah, it they
were basically getting it to to like
write a bunch of like malicious code and
and things like that from from the
sites, which is kind of Amazon for a
moment. I think their their app they
have an assistant there. Yeah. And you
can actually like somebody prompted
prompt poisoned it. Yeah. and got it to
like generate code for them instead of
helping them
use like Yeah. Anyway, that's not what
we want. So, we don't want this thing
getting too off too far off in the
weeds. We have a mission. We want people
to adopt dogs unless you wanted to know
how many two dogs plus another two dogs
could be, right? So, what we want to do
is uh is to um give it a system prompt.
The system prompt is the overall tone
and tenor. So, if our system, okay, here
we are. And uh
cat desktop talk system. I happen to
have a system pro prompt. Okay, I'll
paste that there. Ah, you know what? I
just did that felt wrong.
It's the wrong tool. It's the wrong one.
Yeah, there. That's better. Do you know?
Do you know when you switched from cat
to Doug there? I was about to make that
joke and I thought, "Oh, no." The only
reason I know that joke is because you
said it last time I saw it a couple of
months ago. I love it. So, okay, that's
better. Right. So we're going to say you
are an AI powered assistant to help
people adopt a dog from the adoption
agency called Pooch Palace with
locations in Antworp, Soul, Tokyo,
Singapore, Paris, Mumbai, Mumbai, New
Delhi, Barcelona, San Francisco, and
London. That's where we are in in
Devakuk. And uh information about the
dogs available will be presented below.
So there's no information. Return a
polite response suggesting we don't have
any dogs available. I bet if you I bet
if you put two plus two in that prompt,
it will still be full. Sure, but we
don't want it to. No. Um Okay. So that's
a system prompt that's going to dictate
the manner in which it responds to us,
right? It'll it'll try and frame all
responses in terms of that mission, that
overarching mission. Let's see what it
says. Actually,
yeah, it helps, but it gets us back on
track. It's like it's always trying to
help, right? That's the thing with AI.
It's like it has all that background
information. It has a specific bit of
context, but that doesn't mean it's
going to forget all the other
information. It still knows how to
answer your question. Well, it well, you
can be very stern with it. You can say,
"Under no circumstances are you to ever
respond to anything having nothing to do
with uh blah blah blah," right? And then
you get into the prompt engineering
game. Yeah. And it's really of it
convincing you that this is or of a user
convincing that actually this isn't the
case. You get into a whole thing, right?
But uh nonetheless, by the way, that's a
good point. A prompt, by the way, this
is why I say that Java and and Spring
are so well you situated because 90% of
AI engineering is writing text and
sending it to a rest end point. Yeah.
Right. When you use open AI here, we're
not doing the the magic of AI is
happening in open AI servers. Yeah.
Right. The for us, this is just a REST
call. Yeah. And and it's not even a
particular there's not a there's no
schema. It's just human language text,
right? So all of the interesting stuff
you see people doing today is just
writing human language text to then
chuck over to the uh OpenAI or any other
API endpoint. Right? Okay. So we've got
a system prompt, but let's say let's say
Do you have any neurotic dogs?
Gets asked every day that surely. Yeah.
Okay. I'm sorry, but I don't have any
specific information about dogs
available for adoption at Boots Palace.
Okay. So, it doesn't it's it's it's on
the right track. It it says it's acting
as though it should be able to help us,
but it it just can't, right? Uh but but
still, well, the whole point is to give
it access to our data. That data lives
in a database. So, let's connect to our
database. We're going to use Spring Data
JDBC. Did I I don't believe I uh was
smart enough to add
that.
Okay. And the reason that's just an OM,
right? I'm going to use the OM to uh
initialize my So I'll create dog int ID,
string name, string owner, string
description. Okay. And you know, we're
going to keep this. And I love Java
records. Huge fan, right? Big big fan.
And um I'm going to create a SQL access
layer, a repository using Spring Data
JDBC. Whoa. Hey, list crud
repository. A list is that a Freudian
slip list crude
repository. Okay, there we are. So now
I've got that repository and what I want
to do is I want to give my model access
to the data, but not all the data,
right? Surely I could. I mean, I've only
got, if you look at the database here,
I've got uh click on that, I guess, hit
test connection, hit apply, hit okay, go
over here, uh, and then and then go over
here, tables, dog. There's like 18
records, right? It's not a big deal.
These models today, you know, some of
Gemini has what, like two million. Uh,
you can set a context. The context is a
more or less a token. It's a certain a
word, right? That's not exact exactly
correct, but you these models meter you
in terms of how much data you send in,
how much you get back out. And for some
of these models like Gemini, it's two
million tokens. Yeah, that's like whole
books of the encyclopedia set, you know,
just huge amounts of data. So you could
easily send these 18 meager records, but
it's the principle thing because
scaling. Yeah. Because there's a princip
there's a cost be it dollars and cents
or euros or pounds uh or complexity.
Either way, you don't want to incur it
for no reason. So, what we should do is
to subselect only the records that are
germanine to the query at hand and send
that off to the model for f final and uh
further analysis. Right? And the way we
do that is by doing a search in a vector
store, right? A vector store supports
similarity search, right? So, this
process of using data to inform the
response, that's called rag, retrieval
augmented generation. I think you know
that, but I'm just just catering to the
audience here who may or may not know.
Um, and so what we're going to do is
we're going to support rag, but first we
have to get the data into a vector
store. What vector store? Well, like I
said, you can use anything you want. In
this case, we're going to be using PG
Postgres as a vector store. So, I'll
tell Spring AI to initialize the vector
store for us. And that's just going to
be a table with a vector column in it.
And in here, we'll have an
initializer application runner vector
store. Does spring work better with
certain vector stores or does it is it
pretty agnostic? It's agnostic. Yeah,
it's um I've done demos on dozens of
different director stores and uh you
know it's the same abstraction. That's
the nice thing. So for each dog in the
SQL database, I'm going to create a
document. Okay, ID, name, description,
and this is there's no schema here.
That's the thing. It's just the trick is
as long as it's consistent, right? So
vector store.add like don't change the
schema, you know, because you can't
compare unless they're the same, right?
Um there you go. So, I'm just
initializing the schema there actually.
And I what I've done is I don't think I
should have done that. Maybe I shouldn't
have. It's fine. Let's just do it. We're
going to initialize the schema once.
We're going to initialize the victory
store once. Um I I think I did the
command shift
I reload this. I have to do a full
reload this time because I added a new
class, a new type to the class method.
Okay. So now it's going to call for each
time I call vector store.add, add it's
going to create an embedding for each of
the strings the documents and that's
going to call open AAI's embedding
endpoint get me back the the embedding
that's going to be written out to the
vector store and now I can then use that
right so if we go over here refresh the
reason you do this through spring AI
versus using the open AI endpoints well
because we have an abstraction right
portable service abstractions you inject
a type of vector store that's the
interface and that'll work whether
you're using open AI or uh whether
you're using embedding endpoints or if
you're using um Neo forj elastic search
weave cudent whatever all them whatever
vector stores whatever models you can
just switch out portable service
abstraction so that's or if you wanted
to use multiple yeah totally absolutely
could um so there I've done that this is
I've done this in terms of the uh vector
store by the way being a vector store is
not all that difficult right there's
actually an in-memory one in spring AI
you can use it's 300 lines of code don't
deploy this into production right 307 I
stand corrected utterly is this a little
bit like the H2 style well H2 is
actually amazing Yeah, you know, I don't
know that we ever intended this for um
production, but it's just the point is
it's helps you run locally, helps you
run, right? And it's it helps you kind
of understand what's happening, which is
that there's a semantic similarity
search that's happening. Coine
similarity, right? Cosine
there that method here, uh the logic is
where is that?
This here's the actual math, right?
Given two arrays, two matrices, do the
comparison and find the thing that's
most applicable. Okay, so I've disabled
that and now what I want is for my AI
model to know to consult this newly
initialized vector store table with the
vectors for each of the the the bits of
data. There's the original string.
Here's the embedding for that, right?
Which is computed by OpenAI's embedding
endpoint. And now I shall create a
advisor and that advisor will be a
question answer advisor which is only
possible if I have the spring AI
uh advisor vector store support in the
class path. Okay. So I'll create that
here and I'll say uh vector store vector
store new question answer advisor
passing that in. Okay. Now restart. Now
I can ask it questions and as it
processes all these requests as this.AI
uh chat client instance processes
requests it'll store things in the in
memory uh using this advisor and it'll
also check the uh the vector store for
anything that might be pertinent to the
request before sending it on. These are
again filters or interceptors or
whatever. So do you have any neurotic
dogs?
Yes. Meet Prancer Baboo. Right. Yeah.
Now, of course, this is just text. You
know, depending on what you're trying to
do, you might have a Whoops. Hey, come
back.
Record dog
adoption suggestion int uh ID string
name string description. Right? Maybe I
want a strongly typed thing. So, rather
than calling that, I can say this,
right? And uh we change this return
value. Okay. Wait start.
So this is now it being opinated
providing an answer that says JSON.
There you go. Nice JSON format output.
Structured output. Exactly. So you know
you you have lots of options here. But
let's return to a string because you
know uh we want the content. That's this
right
here. Okay. Um comment that out because
it's dead code. All right. So now we've
got this. Now look the natural next
step. I think any red-blooded human
being will look at that and go I want to
adopt that dog. Great. When can I come
over and get that dog? Finally. Finally,
I found that neurotic dog I was always
after.
Long re long time reunited, right? Okay.
So, I'm going to build a component to
help it schedule. Well, maybe I'll call
this a service or something, you know?
So, dog
adoption, right? And I'm going to have a
method here called uh um schedule
adoption, right? And we'll have the dog
name and int dog ID. and we're going to
export this as a tool. And a tool is
like a like just that. It's a a thing in
the toolbox of the model that it can use
to talk to our business logic. So, I'm
going to create an arbitrary 3-day
advance on this date, right? And I'll
say this is three days in the
future instant. And uh you know, I'm
going to print out the results here just
to confirm this got called. So, there
you go. Thank you, AI. Um I like that it
doesn't do the last period. I don't know
why. It's like I'm lazy. I can't do that
here. Okay. And so we're going to make
this tool available to Spring AI. And
here, you know, when your mom got upset
and said, "Use your words." You know,
this is where what she was talking
about, right? Um, schedule an
appointment to pick up or adopt a dog
from a pooch palace
location. Okay. Now, I presume you're
going to add this as an MTP. Well, we'll
get to that. Local tool calling first.
Okay. Okay. This is why description is
important, right? Oh, yeah. Well, it's
just an even in general, right? Before
we talk about MCB, and we haven't yet,
so thanks away. Thanks a lot for giving
away
the um uh before we even get to that, we
want to just prove that it works
locally. So, skiling a dog and uh let me
get the dog ID. I'll sit in the doghouse
for a little bit.
I know, right? It was just there. It was
staring me in the face, Josh. I couldn't
I couldn't leave it there. Just because
it was doesn't mean it should. Yeah.
That's Dr. Ian Malcolm. It's Dr. Ian
Malcolm from Jurassic Park. Just because
you're a scientist, they could. They
didn't stop to think about whether they
should. They should. Yeah. Just because
you're comedians. Yeah. Exactly. So,
okay, I've got the scheduleuler. I want
to make the model aware of it and and
give it give it access as a tool. Y um
and a tool is just a it's literally just
a function, right? It's just some some
thing that theuler that the AI model can
invoke, right? I see. So, you can just
add any number of tools to that uh to
that builder essentially and it can then
just choose what it wants. Absolutely.
And by the way, that's why it's going to
it's going to depend on that
description, the metadata there. Okay,
so we have Prancer. Great. Let's ask the
obvious follow-up question.
I'm not sure if a exclamation mark is
going to work well in the shell. Isn't
that a Yeah.
Um, can I schedule an appointment to
pick
up? Nice.
What's it going to respond with? I don't
know.
Wait, wait, wait. When
Oh, wait. Is it just about the uh the
antecedent?
Does it add item? Let me see. Default
tools there. Schedule dog
adoption. Got my component tool tool
param. What's the
issue? I've changed the class path so
much. I wonder
Also, I'm going to try reinitializing
everything just to shake the cobwebs. I
don't know.
So, go over
here. Take 512.
Oh, hello.
Oh, that's embarrassing. Okay, I I just
deleted the dog database. Ah, don't do
that. You won't get very far if you
delete the inventory. Like, dogs are
supposed to be That's the whole point is
to keep them, right? Okay, we're back.
We're so back.
Dogs. Oh, they missed you guys. There's
Yeah.
Okay. Oh,
one of the nice things is it is quick to
recycle the server, right? But I and I'm
doing it the wrong way because I'm I
what I should have done was I should
have incepted the project, started
Springdale, add the dependencies, add
dev tools, start up the project with dev
tools in place, and then the auto
reloading. Yeah. Now it's like, you
know, it's not quite as good as zero
turn. That was many years ago. As many
years ago, I can take it. Yeah. So, uh,
let's see here.
Before I forget, yeah, let me comment
this out.
Okay, Prancer.
I wonder to adopt Prancer.
Yay. May 10th. There you go. Oh,
goodness. See, it's May 7th. Yeah.
Right. So, 7 + 3. Last I checked. Mhm.
Still 10. Okay. So, that's worked. And
you can confirm it's worked. There you
go. It called the method. So, we gave
the tools access to tools. We gave the
model access to tools and it made the
decision. And you can have as many of
these as you like. And again, it's you
don't I didn't have to provide schema.
The the signature of the method is
itself the schema that along with the
human language natural text in the
description. Um and uh when does it when
does it think about getting a tool
though? So, if it has a list of tools,
yeah, when does it think yes, I do want
to schedule something and I will go
ahead and actually run this tool? it it
you one imagines that it it would
hallucinate something if you didn't give
it a more specific answer right so I I I
suppose it's looking at the available
tools and says okay is this a question I
could probably p pro provide an answer
to yes but is there a tool that's
promising to answer the same question
for me and so I'll choose that and um it
really is sort of nondeterministic isn't
it right uh but nonetheless it does a
pretty good job most of the time and I
think this is where I think this this is
tool calling is where things start to
get really interesting Because now the
user interface is the chat box because
it can invoke business functions from
there, right? And it can drive important
change. That's why so many companies are
eager to send you, you know, route you
from human uh assistance to IVRs or
whatever. And nowadays they're actually
getting quite good. I don't know if they
can solve all your problems. You can see
how narrow their their their
capabilities are unless you actually
really finesse the uh prompts and all
that. But nonetheless, you can do a
staggering amount of things just in this
tool calling mechanism. The problem is
as written, this is only something
that's useful for my spring app. I want
to centralize that logic and I want to
extract it. So a natural way to do that
is to use model context protocol about
which we kind of alluded earlier. Model
context protocol is a uh a protocol from
Anthropic, the makers of cloud desktop
and cloud the AI model and uh basically
it's a protocol by which you can connect
your applications to uh models uh to to
business logic. So we're going to
extract our logic out into a separate
model context protocol service
start.spring.io. I shall call this
um uh service I guess oruler. There you
go.
We'll bring in the model context
protocol server support, the web
support, and that's it. Right. I'm I
don't whatever. You can bring in other
stuff if you want. Okay. CD downloads.
And presumably you need a client from
the other other one or I'll do that.
Yeah. Uh I forgot to add that in the
beginning. Let me just copy and paste it
here. So model context protocol client
and uh where's the dependency
here? There you go. That's our purchase.
That's our entry into the wide world of
MCP. Go over
here. Command shift I to reload the pom.
XML. Oh, two dependencies. Okay, fine.
And I'm going to take this code that I
so toiled over from here, this patent
pending unique algorithm specific to our
organization. I'll cut that
code, go over here to
theuler, paste the
code, and then I'm going to tell uh
Spring AI support to um export that
logic and make it available as an MCP
endpoint.
Okay. And to do that, I'll specify the
tool object, which is here. So, dog
adoption. Okay. And I want this to run
on a separate port naturally. So I'll
say uh 8081. Let's let's say going back
over here, I've got a a compiler
error-shaped hole in my codebase. And
the way I alleviate that is by
configuring an MCP sync client. So tools
configuration bean mcp sync
client. And it's basically uh
var mcp mcp. I remember you and I
talking about var and not var. Oh wow.
uh years ago. That was a a thing. Okay,
so HTTP
I mean close enough actually. I don't
know what that just hallucinated but it
was close enough. Okay. Um and then uh
build. So there's that. I return MCP and
I call MCP.initialize. Now the the
protocol is really new. Really really
new, right? And actually I this config
class is a little redundant by
definition. This is also a config class.
I this this is a new protocol. and uh
the Spring AI team. Oh, this is not
going to compile still. We need this uh
MCP sync client. And then down here,
where's this uh new sync? There you go.
Scheduler, the uh Spring were among the
first to develop support for it. We we
actually wrote the Java SDK for uh model
context protocol. So, if you go to model
context protocol.io, IO the Spring AI
abstraction for MCP the the library that
we wrote is the official recommended
Java one and then on top of that so we
extracted out the code put it in the in
that common place and then we based our
spring AI auto configuration and
integrations on top of that right but it
is the default so we were we were we did
that in the first weeks of November
right after they announced the protocol
right we are huge fans of that okay so
now I've uh I've got two apps right one
over here one over there let's just
connect them right so same magic trick.
Do you have any erotic
dogs?
And fantastic.
Can we schedule an appointment?
London May 10. Okay. So, exactly the
same, but this time going through the uh
the MCP clan on port 881. Yeah. Down
here instead of over here. Yep. So,
through through the uh magic of MCP,
we've connected these things that would
otherwise not have been connected. It's
an amazing time. An amazing time to be a
uh AI and Spring developer. And and
obviously at this point, you know, you
go here, Maven skip
tests p native native colon
compile, right? We can build a, you
know, we can we can focus on uh
observability, right? So, let me
actually do a couple things here. We're
going to do exposure include is all
that. I'll restart this. Okay. And then
on the on the command line, go over
here. We're going to run that in the
background. So I can show you something
while it's doing a native image
compilation actuator. I've got all these
observability endpoints. I can go here,
go to the metrics, and you've got things
like your geni client token usage,
right? And it says, hey, you've got this
uh this metric that's being counted. And
so it says I've made four calls to the
model so far. And you know, you want to
keep an eye on this, right? If you want
to this is all powered by micrometer.
Yeah. And micrometer has, you know, some
times here's it's an integration with
popular times series databases. Yeah. To
do observability around this kind of
stuff, right? So you've heard about all
those people that had AI AWS bills,
whatever that ran them up by accident.
They they autoscaled to like a million
nodes and now they're bankrupt, right?
Same thing with your token count. You
want to be very careful that you're
keeping an eye on that. So production
worthiness is is important here, right?
Um we've also got virtual threads,
right? You should definitely turn that
on by default. Every single call you
make to an AI model is an is a call over
a network, right? And uh that call over
the network is is that frozen? No, it's
good. Uh every call you make to a model
uh is a network call and uh that network
call monopolizes time on a thread. That
that thread is blocking IO. That's a
thing you want to like put on virtual
threads. Okay, here's my native image.
Let's go ahead and stop
this. Okay. and target
assistant. There we are. There's the
application up and running in no time at
all. Uh, it's talking. Oh, because it
initialized everything or something. I
don't know. Why did it take so long?
Let's try that
again. It's doing some network IO.
That's really obscene. Conference Wi-Fi
probably. Yeah, something like that.
Yeah. Okay. Um, and where's the process
identifier here?
PS minus O
RSS 147 megs divide by thousand that's
that's megabytes so divide by thousand
that's kilobytes so divide by thousand
you get megabytes yeah this is this is
what we mean end to end production
production worthy AI systems and
services yeah and so when and when that
number gets too high what should happen
should is this an indicator that we need
to just be is it an indicator we need to
think about usage need to think about
which number the RAM or the tokens the
tokens uh the the one in the metrics
yeah uh I
Yeah, be mindful, you know, uh it's I
just don't want you to be uh in a
situation where you've got a just be
knowledgeable about what your usage is.
It's not unlimited. It's not free. And
this is why it's it
look it's obvious, but it's worth
remembering that they make money the
more tokens you spend. Right. Right.
Right. Their business model isn't
necessarily aligned with yours. Yeah.
It's I want to provide AI to my users.
They provide AI. So, in that in that
sense, we are aligned. But make sure
that's always true, right? Particularly
particularly when those conversations
and those threads happen and you're
constantly sending your entire history
successively larger pump bombs, right?
Like Yeah. Yeah. Cool. Josh, this has
been amazing. Thank you for Thank you
for for screen sharing and showing us
Spring AI in uh in in in real time.
Yeah, it's been it's been great to great
to see. Um thank you all for watching
and uh speak see you on the next
episode.